Eric Berlow: I'm an ecologist, and Sean's a physicist,
إيريك برلو: أنا عالم بيئه وشون فيزيائي
and we both study complex networks.
و كلينا ندرس الشبكات المعقده
And we met a couple years ago when we discovered
والتقينا قبل بضع سنوات عندما اكتشفنا
that we had both given a short TED Talk
أن كلانا تكلمنا في تيد من قبل
about the ecology of war,
عن البيئة الحربية
and we realized that we were connected
وادركنا أننا كنا على صلة
by the ideas we shared before we ever met.
بالأفكار التي تشاطرناها من قبل ان نلتقي
And then we thought, you know, there are thousands
ومن ثم فكرنا أن هناك آلاف
of other talks out there, especially TEDx Talks,
المحادثات الأخرى حول الموضوع، لا سيما محادثات تيدكس،
that are popping up all over the world.
التي ظهرت في جميع أنحاء العالم.
How are they connected,
كيف ارتبط بعضهم ببعض،
and what does that global conversation look like?
وما شكل تلك المحادثة العالمية؟
So Sean's going to tell you a little bit about how we did that.
سيحدثكم شون قليلا عن كيفية قيامنا بذلك.
Sean Gourley: Exactly. So we took 24,000 TEDx Talks
شون جورليي: تماما. أخذنا 24,000 محادثة لتيدكس
from around the world, 147 different countries,
من جميع أنحاء العالم، من 147 بلد مختلف،
and we took these talks and we wanted to find
وأخذنا هذه المحادثات، وأردنا العثور على
the mathematical structures that underly
الهياكل الرياضية التي من ورائها
the ideas behind them.
الأفكار التي وراءها.
And we wanted to do that so we could see how
وكنا نريد القيام بذلك حتى يمكن أن نرى كيف
they connected with each other.
أنها مرتبطة مع بعضها البعض.
And so, of course, if you're going to do this kind of stuff,
ولذلك، بالطبع، إذا كنت تريد القيام بهذا النوع من الأشياء،
you need a lot of data.
أنت بحاجة إلى الكثير من البيانات.
So the data that you've got is a great thing called YouTube,
تلك البيانات التي تستطيع الحصول عليها من شيء عظيم يسمى يوتيوب،
and we can go down and basically pull
ويمكننا الذهاب إلى أسفل وببساطه نسحب
all the open information from YouTube,
جميع المعلومات المفتوحة من يوتيوب،
all the comments, all the views, who's watching it,
كل التعليقات، جميع الآراء، الاشخاص الذين يشاهدون.
where are they watching it, what are they saying in the comments.
من يشاهد النقاطع، ماذا يقولون في التعليقات.
But we can also pull up, using speech-to-text translation,
ولكن يمكن أيضا سحب - باستخدام ترجمة الكلام إلى نص
we can pull the entire transcript,
يمكن أن نخرج نسخة كاملة من النص
and that works even for people with kind of funny accents like myself.
وهذا يعمل حتى بالنسبة للاشخاص مع لهجات مضحكه مثل نفسي.
So we can take their transcript
لذا يمكننا أن نأخذ النص
and actually do some pretty cool things.
وفي الواقع القيام ببعض الأشياء المذهله
We can take natural language processing algorithms
يمكننا أن ناخذ طريقة ترتيب الكلام واللغه
to kind of read through with a computer, line by line,
إلى نوع من القراءة عن طريق مع جهاز كمبيوتر، سطراً سطراً،
extracting key concepts from this.
لاستخراج المفاهيم الرئيسية منه
And we take those key concepts and they sort of form
ونستعمل تلك المفاهيم الرئيسية، وتكون لنا
this mathematical structure of an idea.
هذا الهيكل الرياضي لفكرة
And we call that the meme-ome.
وندعو أن ميمي-أوم
And the meme-ome, you know, quite simply,
وميمي-اوم كما تعلمون، بكل بساطة،
is the mathematics that underlies an idea,
هو الرياضيات الذي يكمن وراء فكرة،
and we can do some pretty interesting analysis with it,
ويمكننا القيام ببعض التحاليل مثيرة للاهتمام جداً معها،
which I want to share with you now.
وأريد أن اشاركها معك الآن.
So each idea has its own meme-ome,
لذا قد كل فكرة ميمي-اوم الخاصة به،
and each idea is unique with that,
وكل فكرة فريدة من نوعها
but of course, ideas, they borrow from each other,
ولكن بطبيعة الحال، الأفكار، أنها تستلف من بعضها البعض،
they kind of steal sometimes,
أنها نوع من السرقة في بعض الأحيان،
and they certainly build on each other,
وأنها من المؤكد بناء على بعضها البعض،
and we can go through mathematically
ويمكننا أن نذهب من خلال الرياضيات
and take the meme-ome from one talk
وتأخذ ميمي-اوم من نقاش واحد
and compare it to the meme-ome from every other talk,
ونقارن الميمي-اوم من كل نقاش أخرى،
and if there's a similarity between the two of them,
وإذا كان هناك تشابه بين اثنين منهم،
we can create a link and represent that as a graph,
ونستطيع إنشاء ارتباط وتمثل ذلك كرسم بياني،
just like Eric and I are connected.
تماما مثل اتصالي انا و إريك
So that's theory, that's great.
تلك فقط نظرية، هذا أمر عظيم.
Let's see how it works in actual practice.
دعونا نرى كيف يطبق هذا في الممارسة الفعلية.
So what we've got here now is the global footprint
ما لدينا هنا هو حتى الآن الأثر العالمي
of all the TEDx Talks over the last four years
من جميع محادثات TEDx على مر السنوات الأربع الماضية
exploding out around the world
التي تنبع من جميع أنحاء العالم
from New York all the way down to little old New Zealand in the corner.
من نيويورك وصولاً حتى إلى نيوزيلندا
And what we did on this is we analyzed the top 25 percent of these,
وما قمنا به في هذا أننا حلل أعلى 25 في المئة من هؤلاء،
and we started to see where the connections occurred,
وبدأنا نرى المحادثات التي حدثت فيها اتصالات،
where they connected with each other.
حيث أنها مرتبطة مع بعضها البعض.
Cameron Russell talking about image and beauty
كاميرون راسل يتحدث عن الصورة والجمال
connected over into Europe.
متصل عبر أوروبا.
We've got a bigger conversation about Israel and Palestine
لقد حصلنا على محادثة أكبر حول إسرائيل وفلسطين
radiating outwards from the Middle East.
يشع من منطقة الشرق الأوسط.
And we've got something a little broader
ولقد حصلنا على شيء أوسع قليلاً
like big data with a truly global footprint
مثل البيانات الكبيرة مع بصمة عالمية حقاً
reminiscent of a conversation
يذكرنا بمحادثة
that is happening everywhere.
أن ما يحدث في كل مكان.
So from this, we kind of run up against the limits
لذا من هذا، قابلنا نوع من تصادم حدود
of what we can actually do with a geographic projection,
لما يمكن أن نفعل في توقع جغرافي،
but luckily, computer technology allows us to go out
ولكن لحسن الحظ، تكنولوجيا الحاسوب يسمح لنا بالخروج
into multidimensional space.
الى فضاء متعدد الأبعاد.
So we can take in our network projection
لذا يمكن أن نتخذها في بناء شبكة التوقع
and apply a physics engine to this,
وتطبيق محرك فيزياء لهذا،
and the similar talks kind of smash together,
و المحادثات المماثلة ممزوجه معا
and the different ones fly apart,
والمختلفة تبتعد عن بعضها البعض،
and what we're left with is something quite beautiful.
وبقينا مع شيء جميل جداً.
EB: So I want to just point out here that every node is a talk,
لذلك أريد فقط أن أشير هنا أن كل نقطة هي عباره عن حديث،
they're linked if they share similar ideas,
مرتبطة إذا كانت تشاطر أفكار مماثلة،
and that comes from a machine reading
وهذا يأتي من قراءة الجهاز
of entire talk transcripts,
لكامل نقاش النص
and then all these topics that pop out,
وثم كل هذه المواضيع التي تخرج،
they're not from tags and keywords.
أنهم ليسوا من العلامات والكلمات الرئيسية.
They come from the network structure
أنها تأتي من هيكل الشبكة
of interconnected ideas. Keep going.
من الأفكار المترابطة. تستمر.
SG: Absolutely. So I got a little quick on that,
: على الإطلاق. لذلك أنا تعاملت سريعا مع هذا الشأن،
but he's going to slow me down.
ولكنه قال أنه سوف يقوم بإبطائي
We've got education connected to storytelling
لقد حصلنا على التعليم متصلاً بقص الحكايات
triangulated next to social media.
مستنبطة مع وسائل الإعلام الاجتماعية.
You've got, of course, the human brain right next to healthcare,
حصلت، بالطبع، على الدماغ البشري بجوار الرعاية الصحية،
which you might expect,
التي قد تتوقع،
but also you've got video games, which is sort of adjacent,
ولكن كما حصلت على ألعاب الفيديو، وهو نوع من المجاورة
as those two spaces interface with each other.
عندما تلتقي تلك المساحتين.
But I want to take you into one cluster
ولكن أريد أن تأخذهما في كتلة واحدة
that's particularly important to me, and that's the environment.
انها مسألة بالغة الأهمية بالنسبة لي، وهذا هو البيئة.
And I want to kind of zoom in on that
وأريد أن اتوسع في ذلك
and see if we can get a little more resolution.
ونرى إذا كان يمكننا الحصول على قرار أكثر قليلاً.
So as we go in here, what we start to see,
ولذلك كما نرى من هنا، نبدأ في رؤية،
apply the physics engine again,
تطبيق محرك الفيزياء مرة أخرى،
we see what's one conversation
ونحن نرى ما هو محادثة واحدة
is actually composed of many smaller ones.
هي في الواقع تتألف من العديد من الاحاديث الأصغر حجما.
The structure starts to emerge
الهيكل يبدأ في الظهور
where we see a kind of fractal behavior
حيث أننا نرى نوعا من السلوك النمطي المتكرر
of the words and the language that we use
للكلمات واللغة التي نستخدمها
to describe the things that are important to us
لوصف الأشياء المهمة بالنسبة لنا
all around this world.
من جميع أنحاء هذا العالم.
So you've got food economy and local food at the top,
حيث كنت قد حصلت على اقتصاد الأغذية والأغذية المحلية في الجزء العلوي،
you've got greenhouse gases, solar and nuclear waste.
كنت قد حصلت على غازات البيوت الخضراء، والنفايات النووية والشمسية.
What you're getting is a range of smaller conversations,
ما تحصل عليه من مجموعة الأحاديث الأصغر،
each connected to each other through the ideas
كل منهما متصلة ببعضها البعض من خلال الأفكار
and the language they share,
واللغة التي يتقاسمونها،
creating a broader concept of the environment.
خلق مفهوم أوسع للبيئة.
And of course, from here, we can go
وطبعا، من هنا، يمكننا أن ننطلق
and zoom in and see, well, what are young people looking at?
كبر وانظر، أيضا، ما الذي يبحث عنه الشباب؟
And they're looking at energy technology and nuclear fusion.
أنهم يبحثون في تكنولوجيا الطاقة والانصهار النووي.
This is their kind of resonance
وهذا هو النوع الصدى
for the conversation around the environment.
للحديث حول البيئة.
If we split along gender lines,
إذا فرقنا بين الجنسين،
we can see females resonating heavily
يمكننا أن نرى للإناث صدى بشكل كبير
with food economy, but also out there in hope and optimism.
مع اقتصاد الأغذية، ولكن هناك أيضا في الأمل والتفاؤل.
And so there's a lot of exciting stuff we can do here,
وحتى لا يكون هناك الكثير من الأشياء المثيرة يمكن أن نفعله هنا،
and I'll throw to Eric for the next part.
وسوف ننتقل لاريك للجزء القادم.
EB: Yeah, I mean, just to point out here,
ايريك: نعم، يعني فقط أن أشير إلى هنا،
you cannot get this kind of perspective
لا يمكنك الحصول على هذا النوع من منظور
from a simple tag search on YouTube.
من علامة بسيطة لبحث على موقع يوتيوب.
Let's now zoom back out to the entire global conversation
دعونا الآن نعود إلى المحادثة العالمية بأكملها
out of environment, and look at all the talks together.
للخروج من البيئة، وإلقاء نظرة على جميع المحادثات معا.
Now often, when we're faced with this amount of content,
الآن في كثير من الأحيان، عندما نحن نواجه هذا الكم من المحتوى،
we do a couple of things to simplify it.
ونحن نفعل بضعة أشياء لنبسطها
We might just say, well,
ونحن قد نقول فقط، حسنا،
what are the most popular talks out there?
ما هي اكثر المحادثات شعبية هناك؟
And a few rise to the surface.
اتضح لنا عدد قليل منهم إلى السطح.
There's a talk about gratitude.
هناك حديث عن الامتنان.
There's another one about personal health and nutrition.
هناك واحد آخر عن الصحة الشخصية والتغذية.
And of course, there's got to be one about porn, right?
وطبعا، هناك يجب أن يكون هناك حديث عن الإباحية، اليس كذلك؟
And so then we might say, well, gratitude, that was last year.
ولذلك يمكن أن نقول، حسنا، موضوع الامتنان، هذا تم في العام الماضي.
What's trending now? What's the popular talk now?
ما هو الاتجاه الآن؟ ما هو الحديث الاكثر شعبية الآن؟
And we can see that the new, emerging, top trending topic
ويمكننا أن نرى أن المواضيع الجديدة الناشئة التي عليها طلب كثير
is about digital privacy.
هو حول الخصوصية الرقمية.
So this is great. It simplifies things.
هذا شيء عظيم. أنه يبسط الأمور.
But there's so much creative content
ولكن هناك الكثير من المواد الإبداعية
that's just buried at the bottom.
إنها مدفونه في الجزء السفلي.
And I hate that. How do we bubble stuff up to the surface
وأنا أكره ذلك. كيف يمكننا نبرز هذه الأشياء إلى السطح
that's maybe really creative and interesting?
وهذه ربما مبتكرة ومثيرة للاهتمام حقاً؟
Well, we can go back to the network structure of ideas
حسنا، يمكننا أن نعود إلى هيكل شبكة الأفكار
to do that.
للقيام بذلك.
Remember, it's that network structure
تذكر، هو أن هيكل الشبكة
that is creating these emergent topics,
الذي ينشئ هذه المواضيع الناشئة،
and let's say we could take two of them,
ودعونا نقول أننا يمكن أن نأخذ اثنين منهم،
like cities and genetics, and say, well, are there any talks
مثل المدن وعلم الوراثة، ونقول، حسنا، هل هناك أي محادثات
that creatively bridge these two really different disciplines.
.تسد الثغرة بين هذه التخصصات بطريقة ابداعية
And that's -- Essentially, this kind of creative remix
و لهذا-أساسا، هذا النوع من الإبداع في الجمع
is one of the hallmarks of innovation.
واحدة من السمات المميزة للابتكار.
Well here's one by Jessica Green
هنا واحد من جيسيكا جرين
about the microbial ecology of buildings.
حول بيئة الميكروبات للمباني.
It's literally defining a new field.
هو حرفيا تعريف وتخصص جديد.
And we could go back to those topics and say, well,
ويمكن أن نعود إلى تلك المواضيع ونقول حسنا،
what talks are central to those conversations?
ما هي المحادثات المتمركزه حول تلك المحادثات؟
In the cities cluster, one of the most central
في المدن المتكتلة، واحدة من الأكثر مركزية
was one by Mitch Joachim about ecological cities,
كان هناك واحد من ميتش يواكيم حول المدن البيئية،
and in the genetics cluster,
وفي تكتلات علم الوراثة،
we have a talk about synthetic biology by Craig Venter.
ولدينا حديث عن البيولوجيا التركيبية من كريغ فينتر.
These are talks that are linking many talks within their discipline.
هذه هي المحادثات التي تقوم بربط العديد من المحادثات داخل تخصصاتهم.
We could go the other direction and say, well,
يمكن أن نذهب اتجاه الأخرى وأقول، حسنا،
what are talks that are broadly synthesizing
ما هي المحادثات التي تم تحليلها على نطاق واسع
a lot of different kinds of fields.
هناك أنواع مختلفة من الحقول.
We used a measure of ecological diversity to get this.
استخدمنا قدرا من التنوع البيئي للحصول على هذا.
Like, a talk by Steven Pinker on the history of violence,
مثل، حديث من ستيفن بينكر في تاريخ العنف،
very synthetic.
اصطناعية جداً.
And then, of course, there are talks that are so unique
وبعد ذلك، بطبيعة الحال، هناك محادثات فريدة من نوعها
they're kind of out in the stratosphere, in their own special place,
أنهم في اعلى طبقات الغلاف الجوي ، في مكان خاص بهم،
and we call that the Colleen Flanagan index.
ونحن ندعو ذلك بمؤشر كولين فلاناغان
And if you don't know Colleen, she's an artist,
وإذا كنت لا تعرف كولين، انها فنانة،
and I asked her, "Well, what's it like out there
وسألتها، "حسنا، كيف تبدو
in the stratosphere of our idea space?"
في الطبقات العليا لدينا في فضاء الأفكار؟ "
And apparently it smells like bacon.
وعلى ما يبدو أنها تنبعث منه رائحة لحم الخنزير المقدد.
I wouldn't know.
لم أكن أعرف ذلك
So we're using these network motifs
لذلك نحن نستخدم هذه الزخارف الشبكية
to find talks that are unique,
للعثور على المحادثات الفريدة من نوعها،
ones that are creatively synthesizing a lot of different fields,
تلك التي تجمع الكثير من التخصصات المختلفة،
ones that are central to their topic,
تلك التي تتمحور حول موضوعهم،
and ones that are really creatively bridging disparate fields.
وتلك التي هي حقاً تقوم بتوصيل التخصصات المتباينة.
Okay? We never would have found those with our obsession
حسنا؟ نبدأ مع من لديهم نفس هاجسنا
with what's trending now.
مع الاتجاه الحالي
And all of this comes from the architecture of complexity,
وكل هذا يأتي من الهندسة المعمارية لمعقدات الامور،
or the patterns of how things are connected.
أو أنماط التي تصف كيف ترتبط الأشياء.
SG: So that's exactly right.
هذا صحيح تماما
We've got ourselves in a world
هنا نجد أنفسنا في عالم
that's massively complex,
له نطاق واسع ومعقد،
and we've been using algorithms to kind of filter it down
ولقد تم استخدام طرق لتصفيتها
so we can navigate through it.
حتى يمكننا التنقل خلالها
And those algorithms, whilst being kind of useful,
وهذه الطرق، نوعا ما مفيده
are also very, very narrow, and we can do better than that,
أيضا محدودة النطاق جداً، ويمكننا أن نفعل أفضل من ذلك،
because we can realize that their complexity is not random.
لأننا يمكن أن ندرك أن تعقيداتها ليست عشوائية.
It has mathematical structure,
لها بنية رياضية،
and we can use that mathematical structure
ويمكن أن نستخدم هذا الهيكل الرياضي
to go and explore things like the world of ideas
لاستكشاف أشياء مثل عالم الأفكار
to see what's being said, to see what's not being said,
لمعرفة ما يقال، لمعرفة ما لا يقال،
and to be a little bit more human
وأن نكون أكثر إنسانية
and, hopefully, a little smarter.
ونأمل ايضا، أذكى قليلاً.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)